Okay, so דף כג, daf khof gimmel, today's דף daf is דף
כג. daf khof gimmel. We pick up the very last line of
דף כב עמוד ב. daf khof bet amud bet. And the question
is how you understand, this is like a core question, halakhic question,
conceptual issue, how you understand the מצוה mitzvah of נר חנוכה. Ner
Chanukah. What is the מצוה? mitzvah? So actually נר חנוכה Ner Chanukah
is interesting in two respects. One is who are the people that
are obligated? The גמרא Gemara before said, you know, נר איש וביתו,
Ner Ish U'beito, one man per house. But then you had every
person in the house. And then you had whatever, מהדרין מן המהדרין.
mehadrin min hamehadrin. So who's obligated? We'll get back to that in
a minute. What is the obligation, to do what? So here the
גמרא Gemara framed it is is it הדלקה עושה מצוה, Hadlaka Oseh
Mitzvah, the act of lighting, or הנחה עושה מצוה, Hanacha Oseh Mitzvah,
the act of putting down, which is funny, let's say you don't
even have to put it down, let's say it's already down. But
the גמרא Gemara seems to be taking that literally as somehow there's
an act of putting down, although I'll qualify that or reflect on
that in a minute. So two possibilities that the גמרא Gemara had
or two ways that this might make a difference is what if
you lit it in a place that wasn't כשר, kosher, inside your
house, at a time when inside your house is not כשר? kosher?
And then, you know, and then you moved it with the bottom
last line of דף כב עמוד ב. daf khof bet amud bet.
Last line of דף כב עמוד ב. daf khof bet amud bet.
And then you moved it, and then you moved it from inside
your house to outside your house to the right place. So the
act of lighting was not correct, but the putting down was correct.
So in theory, that should be a difference. But the גמרא Gemara
found a way to make it not a difference. Even if it's
the act of putting down, since you're carrying it from inside to
outside, it looks like you're using it as a torch and it
doesn't look like a מנורה, menorah, so it doesn't even work even
from the perspective of הנחה. Hanacha. Okay, and then they had another
flip scenario as well where you were where you where you lit
it standing up and then you put it down in some or
not flip actually essentially the same, just in reverse. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues, תא שמע. Ta Shma. Okay, so it says like
this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. תא שמע, Ta Shma,
come and hear, דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben
Levi, said רבי יהושע בן
לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, עששית שהייתה דולקת והולכת כל היום כולו.
ashsishih shehayta doleket veholechet kol hayom kulo. So if you had a
lantern that was that was burning, right, that was burning from ערב
חנוכה erev Chanukah and it was, you know, it was continuously burning,
maybe it was burning all so כולו. kulo. So למוצאי שבת, lemotzei
Shabbat, מכבה ומדליקה. mechaba u'madlika. So it was burning through שבת, Shabbat,
okay, because obviously you couldn't have, you know, be lighting things on
שבת, Shabbat, so you had a nice 24-hour lantern or 48-hour lantern
and come מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbat you want to use it for
נר חנוכה. Ner Chanukah. You have to extinguish it and relight it.
So אי אמרת בשלמא הדלקה עושה מצוה, Ei Amart Bishlama Hadlaka Oseh
Mitzvah, if you say the lighting is a מצוה mitzvah is the
מצוה, mitzvah, שפיר shapir then I understand. It's not enough that it
was lit from ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. אלא אי אמרת הנחה עושה
מצוה, Ela Ei Amart Hanacha Oseh Mitzvah, if you say the placing
down is a מצוה, mitzvah, so היי מכבה ומדליקה, high mechaba u'madlika,
what do you mean you have to extinguish it and light it?
מכבה ומגביה ומניח ומדליקה מבעיא, mechaba u'magbia u'mani'ach u'madlika mibaya, sorry.
You should have to extinguish it, lift it up, put it down,
and then light it, meaning you're missing what you have to define
as the act of the מצוה. mitzvah. You said the act of
the מצוה mitzvah is putting it down, so you should have to
do all of that. So
now you could have also said, why do you even have to
do all of that? Take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. Lift it
up and put it down. Thank you. Take a look at תוספות.
Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר אמאי מכבה וחוזר ומדליקה. Ve'im Tomar
Amay Mechaba V'chozer Madlika. If all it is is about lighting is
about putting down, בהגבהה סגי, bahagbaha sagi, you just pick it up
and put it down, כיון דהנחה עושה מצוה. kivan dehanacha oseh mitzvah.
So תוספות Tosafot says, תוספות Tosafot says, ויש לומר דמאי שהדליקה מתחילה
לאו לצורך שבת. ve'yesh lomar demarei she'hidlika mitchila lo letzerach Shabbat. תוספות
Tosafot says a scenario that this was not a חנוכה Chanukah lighting
initially was a שבת Shabbat light. So even though even if it's
from the approach that it's a מצוה mitzvah to put down, put
what down? Put down something that's defined as a חנוכה Chanukah light.
So therefore here we accept that it was a שבת Shabbat light
not a חנוכה Chanukah light. So you have to relight it to
define it as a חנוכה Chanukah light. But what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is is that that should not be enough if הנחה
עושה מצוה. Hanacha Oseh Mitzvah. It's not enough to light. So on
the one hand if הנחה עושה מצוה Hanacha Oseh Mitzvah the גמרא
Gemara says it shouldn't matter if the act of הדלקה hadlaka was
done in an unacceptable in a non-acceptable way. It should matter how
the act of הנחה hanacha is done. Or on the other hand
הנחה hanacha seems to be an additional requirement that we haven't heard
of until now, some act of putting down. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. ועוד, Ve'od, and in addition מדקא מברכינן אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להדליק נר של חנוכה. midekamivarchinan asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu
lehadlik ner shel Chanukah.
So from the fact that the ברכה bracha is להדליק נר של
חנוכה, lehadlik ner shel Chanukah, שמע מינה הדלקה עושה מצוה. shma mina
Hadlaka Oseh Mitzvah.
We hear that it's the act of lighting because that's clear from
the ברכה bracha להדליק, lehadlik, שמע מינה, shma mina,
that's a good proof. And now the גמרא Gemara ends and says
והשתא דאמרינן הדלקה עושה מצוה, Vehasta de'amininan Hadlaka Oseh Mitzvah, now that
you're saying it's about the act of lighting, הדליקה חרש שוטה וקטן
לא עשה ולא כלום. hidlika cheresh shoteh vekatan lo asa velo klum.
If a somebody who is not obligated lights it, חרש שוטה וקטן,
cheresh shoteh vekatan, then it's not good. If it were הנחה, Hanacha,
who cares who lights it? Meaning maybe like תוספות Tosafot says it
was lit for a different purpose and defined differently, defined as a
שבת Shabbat light, fine, that's not good. But it's not about the
act of lighting. So even if somebody who's not obligated lights. lights
it, as long as it's defined as a חנוכה Chanukah light, that
was his intent, that wasn't the act of the מצוה. mitzvah. So
fine, so it shouldn't be a problem, you pick it up, you
put it down, and you're done. So but now that we say
it is the act of lighting, then if they light it, it's
no good. אשה ודאי מדליקה, Isha vadai madlika,
but a woman certainly could light, she certainly is obligated, and even
if you focus on the act, a woman is obligated in the
act and her lighting is good, why? דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, נשים חייבות בנר
חנוכה, nashim chayavot bener Chanukah, women are obligated in the מצוה mitzvah
of חנוכה, Chanukah, שאף הן היו באותו הנס, she'af hen hayu be'oto
hanes, even they were in the miracle. So let me go and
sort of now move back and talk about the different component about
what we just said. Okay, so first of all,
in terms of the issue about what does it mean the contrast
of הדלקה hadlaka and הנחה? hanacha? It's quite clear the גמרא Gemara
really interprets הנחה hanacha literally, that somehow there's this new act of
putting it down, so that the גמרא Gemara can even consider the
idea that you can take something, you have to relight it, and
relighting it is not enough, you have to actually lift it up
and put it down. So that becomes a little strange, I mean,
although that is clear, you know, the פשט pshat of the גמרא,
Gemara, why would I think that there's an act to placing it
down? Why, you know, why should that act be significant? Now what
I should say is that some, you know, in a more sort
of contemporary לומדות Lomdus approach, which likes sort of would like likes
to try to define this difference, this debate slightly differently,
and likes to sort of connect it to the earlier debate about
whether when it's extinguished you have to relight it or not, and
to say the following: Is it the act of lighting or is
it the fact that it is burning? It is the fact of
being lit. Okay, if you think about the debate we had earlier
about when it extinguishes do you have to relight it, that really
is could is seems to be what that's debating, right? If I
lit it correctly and it had the potential of going the whole
time, then and done, that was my act, my act was lighting
it. Okay, if it would have definitely gone out, maybe it wasn't
a good lighting, but if it should have stayed and gone and
something happened and then it blew out, that's not my responsibility, I
did the מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah which was lighting. The other possibility
is that no, it's not it's not it's not or it's not
only the act of lighting, it's that they are burning for a
period of time. The גמרא Gemara assumed they had to burn the
entire time from שקיעה עד דתכלה רגל מן השוק, shkia ad detichleh
regel min hashuk, and if it stops burning, you have to relight
it, means it's your responsibility to see that it is burning. The
מצוה mitzvah is to make sure that they are burning, not to
do the act of lighting. It makes a lot of sense that
the מצוה mitzvah is to make sure that they are burning, why?
Because it's פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, right? If you light it and
it blows out immediately, you did your act, you had the potential
of פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, but so okay, so from your perspective,
it's easier if we just focus on the act, but in terms
of what it's going to accomplish, it makes sense that the responsibility
is to ensure that it is burning. So and that is the
debate of whether it blows out you have to relight it. We
rule you do not have to relight it, which is consistent with
what we rule here, which is that it is the act of
lighting. But that you understand, if it's about making sure that it
burns, who cares if a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan light
it? Let somebody who's not obligated light it, light it indoors and
move it outdoors, it's not the moment when it was lit, it's
that you have something that is burning this entire period of time.
So those those approaches, הנחה hanacha and כבתה זקוק לה, kavta zakuk
lah,
that if it goes out you're responsible, and it seems to line
up, that it's a question about the act. You do the act,
you're done, the act has to be done properly, afterwards not your
responsibility. Versus, no, you have to make sure that it burns for
the period of time and therefore the act itself is not so
per se significant. The problem is, of course, as we saw, that
the גמרא Gemara sort of speaks about, oh, if it's הנחה, hanacha,
you light it, you relight it, you pick it up, you put
it down, seems to talk about an act of הנחה, hanacha, not
just about this issue about the duration, about the ensuring of its
burning. But nevertheless, it's worth noting the parallel and the nice two
ways about thinking about that. Yes, Charles?
If הנחה hanacha were really a requirement, it would be a problem
to have a permanent מנורה menorah outside your house.
Right, I mean, that's always, yeah, exactly, like where have we ever
heard this idea that you must sort of lift it and put
it down and all of that, you know, so that is, you
know, that's definitely very strange. But yeah, I don't know why, but
yes, correct, yes.
How did they actually light? If they didn't have an existing flame
in the house left from שבת? Shabbos? We know from the מנורה
Menorah they lit from the מזבח, Mizbeach, something, there was a fire
burning, but in a home?
I mean, how did they make fire before matches?
It was a big deal.
Yeah, I don't know the answer to that, Charlie probably knows. I
mean, I assume the technology had gotten beyond rubbing two sticks together.
It may have been difficult though, that's maybe why they ask the
question if you have a light left from שבת, Shabbos, you have
to blow it out?
Right, but according to both of the opinions in the גמרא, Gemara,
you blew it out, the only difference was whether you also had
to lift it up and put it down. Yes, so I don't
know
the
answer to the flame question.
No, I'm saying that that doesn't explain, it explains why you de-emphasize
the act of lighting, but not explain why I said lighting. Okay.
So now I'm not done.
I'm not done.
Now moving on to the next point of the גמרא Gemara about
bringing a proof from the נוסח הברכה. nusach habracha. That's a very
reasonable thing to do if you want to get an understanding of
how to define the act of the מצוה, mitzvah, let's look at
the נוסח הברכה. nusach habracha. There's an excellent example about that in
the ראשונים Rishonim when it comes to the מצוה mitzvah of שופר,
shofar, where there's a question about whether the מצוה mitzvah of שופר
shofar is to blow שופר shofar or to hear the שופר. shofar.
And so, you know,
the רמב"ם Rambam was asked this question. Anyway, and he proves from
various גמרות Gemaras that the מצוה mitzvah is to blow the שופר
shofar and therefore he says therefore we make the ברכה, bracha, you
know, li- I'm sorry, excuse me, I got that wrong. That the
מצוה mitzvah is the מצוה mitzvah is to hear the שופר shofar
and that's why we make the ברכה bracha לשמוע קול שופר lishmoa
kol shofar and that there's this direct connection between what how we
define what the מצוה mitzvah is and what the נוסח הברכה nusach
habracha is. Others actually say we make the ברכה bracha of לתקוע
litkoa or על תקיעת שופר. al tekias shofar. So and would
and argue that the מצוה mitzvah is to blow, not to hear.
With that being said, and it obviously makes sense to assume that
there is a that the nature of the מצוה mitzvah is reflected
in the נוסח הברכה, nusach habracha, there are times where we are
not so precise. I'll just give you two examples. There's some times
where we refer to the act although the מצוה mitzvah is not
really the act is not the idea of the מצוה mitzvah is
not it's not the act that we are describing. When you put
on ציצית, tzitzit, the ברכה bracha you make is להתעטף בציצית lehitatef
betzitzit to wrap yourself with ציצית. tzitzit. There is not a מצוה
mitzvah to wrap yourself with ציצית. tzitzit. The מצוה mitzvah is when
you are wearing a four-cornered garment, you have to make sure that
there are ציצית tzitzit on the garment. There's no מצוה mitzvah to
pick up some garment and wrap yourself with ציצית. tzitzit. Okay, so
there the ברכה bracha reflects the act that you are doing even
if it is not necessarily the point the conceptual definition of the
מצוה. mitzvah. Another example of an exception what?
How else could you frame it?
על מצות ציצית? al mitzvat tzitzit? על מצות ציצית al mitzvat tzitzit
is always a good generic. Okay. Another what?
What you do a ברכה bracha on?
What you do if on bitz- we do on טלית קטן? tallit
katan?
On
ערב פסח erev Pesach when we go and check for חמץ, chametz,
what ברכה bracha do we make?
על ביעור חמץ. al biyur chametz. That's not the act that we're
doing. But there, the act that we're doing is to check. But
there, right, that actually is nice because there there's a difference between
the act and the point the קיום kiyum of the act as
we would say, the conceptual idea of what you are doing, what
you are doing is part of the process of ביעור חמץ, biyur
chametz, and there we do emphasize not the focus on the concrete
act but on conceptually what you are doing. Anyway, but it is
so just to point out that while it's not always a complete
one-to-one correspondence, it does it is nice and it does make sense
to assume that the נוסח הברכה nusach habracha reflects exactly how the
מצוה mitzvah is defined. Charlie, you wanted to say something about how
did they make fire?
Matches are only 150 years old.
I'm trying to find what did they do before that.
Flint was used.
Okay. So that was certainly an idea of rubbing two sticks together.
Okay. Now,
I mean, I think in the משנה Mishnah you already have it
because the משנה Mishnah talks about banging two rocks together and making
a spark. So anyway, by שבת. Shabbos. Anyway, oh we are in
מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbos, look at that. Anyway,
okay actually but no that context I think was יום טוב, Yom
Tov, but anyway. Okay fine. So now let's say something about women
and אף הן היו באותו הנס. af hein hayu be-oto hanes. So
first of all, what does אף הן היו באותו הנס af hein
hayu be-oto hanes mean? There's two basically explanations in the ראשונים. Rishonim.
One means that they were the people that that you know that
they were saved by the miracle, that the גזירת חנוכה gezeirat Chanukah
was you know about
restricting you know basically Jewish practice and observance and the נס, nes,
I mean if you wanted to focus on the נס nes of
the פך השמן pach hashemen that occurred to all of כלל ישראל,
Klal Yisrael, but the נס nes of the war also gave them
freedom and freedom of practice and gave them back their you know
their
self-governance and all of that. So obviously they were the beneficiaries of
the נס nes together with everyone else. Right, רש"י Rashi says it.
That's one explanation. There's another explanation which is also hinted to in
רש"י Rashi which is they were part of the vehicles of the
נס. nes. The גמרא Gemara uses אף הן היו באותו הנס af
hein hayu be-oto hanes in three cases. Does anybody know?
Right, about which מצוה mitzvah by פסח? Pesach? Do you know? ארבע
כוסות. arba kosot. Do you know why they have an ארבע כוסות?
arba kosot? By here and by פורים. Purim. Right. Now by פורים
Purim it's obvious why אף הן היו באותו הנס af hein hayu
be-oto hanes in the in the sense that they were the the
vehicles of the redemption by Esther. By פסח, Pesach, those that take
this approach quote נשים צדקניות נגאלו אבותינו ממצרים. nashim tzidkaniyot nigalu avoteinu
miMitzrayim.
Here רש"י, Rashi, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says,
first he says שגזרו יוונים על בתולות הנישאות להיבעל לטפסר תחילה, she-gazru
Yevanim al betulot hanissuot lehibael latofsar techila, that that was one of
the edicts that
they would have
to... Holofernes? Yeah. Holofernes? Yeah. Oh yeah, is that his name? Okay.
Okay, fine.
Anyway, good.
Okay,
fine.
Anyway, so, so now the question becomes
there's two questions about אף הן היו באותו הנס af hen hayu
be-oto ha-nes as a reason. Number one, why do we need it?
Okay, because normally you'd say it's מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא, mitzvot aseh
she-hazman grama, it's timed, and this solves the problem. Okay, fine. But
now the question is, so, you know, why not use it... תוספות
Tosafot asks in other places. Why, for example, is a woman not
obligated in סוכה Sukkah and לולב, Lulav, אף הן היו באותו הנס?
af hen hayu be-oto ha-nes? Why, for example, when we did say
אף הן היו באותו הנס af hen hayu be-oto ha-nes in פסח,
Pesach, did we need that... so we use that to explain ארבע
כוסות, Arba Kososos, why don't we use it to explain why women
are חייב chayyav in מצה? Matzah? We learn מצה Matzah from a
פסוק, pasuk, right? That if you're prohibited in חמץ, Chametz, you're obligated
in מצה. Matzah. Why don't we say אף הן היו באותו הנס?
af hen hayu be-oto ha-nes? What is the scope of this and
why does it apply in some cases and not in other cases?
That's a question תוספות Tosafot raises. So תוספות'ס Tosafot's answer to this
is that we really only use it for rabbinic מצוות. mitzvot. If
you think all three of these are rabbinic: פורים, Purim, חנוכה, Chanukah,
and ארבע כוסות. Arba Kososos. And his basic point is is that
when we're dealing with biblical מצוות, mitzvot, if there's a general rule
of מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvot aseh she-hazman grama and so on,
and that basically defines two categories, so we're not going to use
אף הן היו באותו הנס af hen hayu be-oto ha-nes to somehow,
you know, change that division. But if we're the rabbis and we're
making the obligation to begin with, we're going to consider the point
of אף הן היו באותו הנס af hen hayu be-oto ha-nes from
the outset to define who are the people that are obligated and
לכתחילה lechatchila we'll obligate men and women equally. That's essentially what תוספות
Tosafot is... not תוספות Tosafot here, תוספות Tosafot in פסחים Pesachim with
a little elaboration from me. But a nice, you know, very nice
explanation maybe building on תוספות, Tosafot, maybe a variation of תוספות, Tosafot,
was said by רב סולובייצ'יק, Rav Soloveitchik, which is is that all
three of these also share another common denominator in addition to being
rabbinic: that they all have the element of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa.
Okay, so clearly פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa is why we say על
הנסים al ha-nissim in חנוכה Chanukah and פורים, Purim, and that the
מגילה Megillah is you know it's part of that and right and
right
and and actually what I meant to say was not just we
say על הנסים al ha-nissim we say we say שעשה
נסים לאבותינו,
she-asah nissim
la-avoteinu, right, thank you, when we do the מצווה, mitzvah, because the
מצווה mitzvah of הדלקה hadlaka and the מצווה mitzvah of מגילה Megillah
are to be מפרסם הנס mefarsem hanes and that's how it's described
in the גמרא. Gemara. But even the ארבע כוסות, Arba Kososos, even
though it's not as much of a פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa to
people outdoors, you know, but it's part of this idea להראות עצמו
כאילו הוא יצא ממצרים le-har'ot atzmo ke-illu hu yatza mi-Mitzrayim and to
demonstrate the freedom has this quality of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. And
that explains very much the connection. If it's fundamentally not just about,
oh, it's an obligation, this happened, you gotta do this, but if
the point is to to you know to publicize the miracle, then
you want to include as large of a group as possible in
the aspect of פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa and you want to include
everybody that was part of the miracle in the obligation of פרסומי
ניסא. pirsumei nisa. So that's a nice explanation about why this is
the why you know this idea of אף הן היו באותו הנס
af hen hayu be-oto ha-nes is used in some contexts and not
in other contexts.
Yes, right, but according to here, I mean it seems to me,
you know, there's a different take on this. They say וודאי מדליק
vadai madlik mean לכתחילה lechatchila because this was a time where there's
only one person lighting for the whole house. So it could be
the man, it could be the woman. So why was there so
much hesitancy, you know, among or is there not? It seems to
me there's hesitancy among, you know, some of the אשכנזי Ashkenazi פוסקים
poskim that you know that then the woman of the house light
if there's the man of the house. I mean I'm not saying
it's warranted, but as to why.
Yeah, so I don't know what that's based on. You know, there's
hesitancy about a woman making קידוש Kiddush even though it's obvious a
woman can make קידוש, Kiddush, so it might have to come from
some ideas about צניעות tzniut or whatever but not strictly sort of
halakhic in terms of in terms of the you know opportunity. It
might also have to do with the fact that, and this is
as I said a confusing part that we'll get to a little
later, we've already gotten to, is who are what how do you
understand the nature of the obligation? I mean is it that the
household is obligated, one person lights for the house? Is it that
each person is obligated? It can't be each person is obligated, then
how could you be יוצא yotzei with one person lighting? But when
you move from the normal to the מהדרין, mehadrin, does it switch
the people of the obligation does it switch who's obligated? At the
first level, the household was obligated. At the second level of מהדרין
מן המהדרין, mehadrin min ha-mehadrin, then everybody becomes obligated individually and so
on. Anyway, if the idea... so that's a whole interesting question how
do you think about who's obligated. But if you think about that
it's somehow the household, it could be that, you know, even if
even if a woman is obligated or could do the מצווה mitzvah
for the household, you know, they want to see the man as
the head of the house. So maybe that has an additional idea
even beyond like the קידוש, Kiddush, because here it's talking about it
as a unit of a household rather than as individuals, and maybe
it's a desire to see it that way. But from the גמרא
Gemara you don't see that, and actually let's keep on reading in
the גמרא Gemara about this. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, so
said רב ששת Rav Sheshet exactly on this topic of who's
obligated: אכסנאי חייב בנר חנוכה. achsannai chayyav be-ner Chanukah. A guest, you're
staying at somebody's house, you have to light נר חנוכה. ner Chanukah.
Now this is going to assume that you don't have people lighting
for you back at home. You're just a single guy out on
the street and you're staying at somebody's house. רש״י, Rashi, by the
way, adds, or not רש״י, Rashi, I don't think רש״י Rashi adds
this, but some פוסקים poskim add that this is when you have
a separate room and a separate exit and entrance because this gets
to the whole question about the whole idea of your doorway, your
doorway leading to the street. If that were not the case, again,
this makes it sound like you're חייב chayav as an individual and
not חייב chayav as part of a household. It's not the household
is obligated, the house has to have חנוכה Chanukah lights. If you
say when I'm going, you know, and I'm going to Atlanta and
I'm staying at somebody's house I've got to light, so you're saying
I have a חיוב chiyuv to light, not my house has a
חיוב chiyuv to light. So that's why even if I'm single, but
you know, this isn't my house, I'm staying at somebody else's house,
he's lighting for the house, why should I have to light? So
that's why some פוסקים poskim say that we're talking that I've got
a separate entrance and an exit and my own room, and therefore
maybe I also have somewhat of my own little house here, but
that's not in the גמרא. Gemara. So it is a little thing
that the פוסקים poskim have to work out whether it's an individual
obligation or a household obligation. Let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, מריש כי הוינא בי רב, mereish
ki haveina bei Rav, when I used to be like a ישיבה
yeshiva student at the house of רב, Rav, meaning at the ישיבה
yeshiva of רב, Rav, and I was a single guy, משתתפנא בפריטי
בהדי אושפיזא. mishtatfana befritei bahadi ushpiza.
I would contribute with some coins, with a few pennies, to my
host. And therefore I would have a portion in the נר חנוכה.
ner Chanukah. Now that makes sense. He's lighting for the household, you're
staying there, you become an extended member of the household, so the
lighting of the household is working for you as well. And maybe
the giving of the coins is to somehow officially make you as
part of this lighting since you're not a natural member, you're passing
through, you're not part of the biological family, whatever what makes you
a part of it? You contribute a little, therefore you're part of
this household, it makes you part of the lighting. But there at
least it's an idea of one candle for the house and that
makes you part of the house. That's what I used to do,
I contributed some pennies. Okay. בתר
דנסבי איתתא, Batar denasbi itata, after I got married and I would
still sometimes go away from home to go to learn at ישיבה
yeshiva for a week or two, anyway,
דנסבי איתתא, denasbi itata, I married a woman, אמינא, amina, I said,
השתא ודאי לא צריכנא, hashta vadai lo tzrichna,
now I don't have to worry about it, דקמדליקי עלי בגו ביתאי,
dekamadlikei alai bego beisai, they are lighting for me at home. So
as long as I don't have to be physically in the home,
my house, my home, even if it's, you know, miles away, has
a light, it has חנוכה Chanukah light being done there. So this
again, the last two make a lot of sense, I mean this
whole last opinion, which basically says the obligation is on the home,
you know, on the people of the home as a corporate unit,
not as individuals. If you're a guest somewhere, you contribute, you become
part of that household. But if you have members of your household
that are lighting for you, then that's your primary home and you
don't even have to be there, your home is, there's a חנוכה
Chanukah light taking place in your home and it's not an obligation
of the individual, at least not at the base level. When you
move to מהדרין mehadrin and מהדרין מן המהדרין, mehadrin min hamehadrin, maybe
yes. Okay, why the initial position said as a guest you have
to light separately then becomes a little bit complicated, why you would
light separately. As I gave some answer to that about a separate
entrance. I should also say again that it becomes questionable why when
we light individuals each person makes a ברכה. bracha. If it really
is an obligation in the home, then that's five ברכות שאינן צריכות,
brachos she'einan tzrichos, you know,
because the home light, we have a couple of extra lights, which
is why the רמב״ם Rambam says one person lights for the people
in the home, but he does not say that you actually, each
individual lights because it still remains the obligation one corporate obligation, not
multiple separate obligations. But it does seem our מנהג minhag or our
practice to make each individual a ברכה bracha means that you can
shift it from an obligation on the home to an obligation on
the individuals and that creates interesting discussion in the פוסקים. poskim.
But then there's an ענין inyan of פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa and
wouldn't you think you should still be lighting anyway, especially the way
you constructed this scenario, his own entrance, you know?
If it's his own entrance, yes, and that's what we just said
a minute ago.
No, but he said, I got married, I don't have to worry
about it.
No, no, that was a separate case. That was not the first
דעת, da'as, that was not רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, that was רב
זירא. Rav Zeira.
Right, I know, I understand, but for רב זירא, Rav Zeira, why
רב זירא Rav Zeira didn't still light, but he was never lighting
separately anyway, he was always contributing. All you're saying is isn't it
nicer if more people light? Fine, that's מהדרין. mehadrin. We're at base
level. אמר רב יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rav Yehoshua ben Levi, said
רב יהושע בן לוי, Rav Yehoshua ben Levi, כל השמנים כולן יפין
לנר. kol hashemanim kulan yafein laner.
All oils are good for the candle. Now it's clear we're still
in the חנוכה Chanukah context. You could think we're shifting back to
שבת, Shabbat, but it's clear from the continued conversation and what comes
after we're still in the חנוכה Chanukah context. All oils are
good, ושמן זית מן המובחר, veshemen zayit min hamuvchar, but olive oil
is ideal, is choice. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מריש הוה
מהדר מר אמשחא דשומשמי. mereish hava mehadar mar amishcha deshumshemi. So originally
the master,
presumably רבה, Rabbah, would prefer to use sesame oil. אמר האי משח
נהורא טפי. Amar hai mashach nehora tfei. Why? Because it burns slow.
Longer. And maybe for פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa you want them to
burn as long as possible. Longer is better? No, longer. כיוון
דשמעיה להא דרבי Keivan deshameih leha de-Rabbi Joshua ben Levi, once he
heard the statement of Rabbi Joshua ben Levi, מהדר אמשחא דזיתא, mehader
amshcha dezaita, now he looks specifically for olive oil. Why? Because he
said, he said olive oil is best. אמר האי צליל נהורא טפי
Amar hai tzalil nehora tefei because it gives a cleaner, a brighter
light. So this is interesting, which is better for פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei
nisa, to burn longer or to burn better? So he said now
that we heard Rabbi Joshua ben Levi was praising olive oil, we
look for olive oil that gives a cleaner light even if it's
not a, even if it burns, does not burn for as long.
I thought that's not a matter of cleanliness, but just a matter
of because like the miracle happened with olive oil.
All right, so that's some, so some ראשונים rishonim say that, but
that's not what's being said here. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Va-amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, כל השמנים יפים לדיו. kol hashemanim yafim ledyo.
Now on a related topic, all oils are good for making ink,
ובשמן זית מן המובחר, u-veshemen zayit min hamuvchar, but olive oil is
ideal. So איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they asked: לגבל או לעשן? legabel
o le-ashen? Is it to mix the ink or is it to
create the smoke? Rashi says what they would do is they would
burn, they would light a fire with olive oil or with some
oil and they would put like a glass on top of it
and then the soot would collect on the glass and then they
would scrape off that soot and then mix it with some type
of mixture that also had some oil in it and somehow through
that make the ink. So here they were in the Gemara asking
that olive oil is preferable, is it for making the smoke or
is it for mixing it with the soot? So it says תא
שמע דתני רב שמואל בר זוטרא, Ta shema de-tani Rav Shmuel bar
Zutra, כל השמנים יפים לדיו ושמן זית מן המובחר. kol hashemanim yafim
ledyo ve-shemen zayit min hamuvchar.
All oils are good, but olive oil is the best. בין לגבל
בין לעשן, Bein legabel bein le-ashen, whether it's for mixing, whether it's
for making smoke. רב שמואל בר זוטרא מתני הכי, Rav Shmuel bar
Zutra matni hachi, and רב שמואל בר זוטרא Rav Shmuel bar Zutra
taught the following: כל העשנים יפים לדיו, Kol ha-ashenim yafim ledyo, all
smokes are good for using as the, you know, for the black
of the ink, ושמן זית מן המובחר, ve-shemen zayit min hamuvchar, but
ideally to use the olive oil to make the smoke. אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, כל השרפים יפים לדיו, kol hasrafim yafim ledyo,
all types of either sap or Rashi says gum, like they would
have a gum basis to the ink, are good, ושרף קטף יפה
מכולם, ve-sraf kataf yafeh mikulam, but the sap of a balsam
is better than all of them. So now you have some of
the ingredients and procedures of making ink. Back to the point. אמר
רבי חלבו אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Chelbo amar Rav, המדליק נר של
חנוכה צריך לברך. hamadlik ner shel Chanukah tzarich levareich. So we sort
of already assumed this above, but now we're saying it, when you
light Chanukah candles you have to make a ברכה. berachah. רבי ירמיה
אמר, Rabbi Yirmiyah amar, הרואה נר של חנוכה צריך לברך. haroeh ner
shel Chanukah tzarich levareich. When you see it, you have to make
a ברכה, berachah, presumably that you did not make a ברכה berachah
when you lit it, or you didn't light, you're a guest, something
of that nature. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, יום ראשון הרואה
מברך שתים, yom rishon haroeh mevareich shtayim, on the first day the
person who sees it makes two ברכות, berachot, והמדליק מברך שלש. ve-hamadlik
mevareich shalosh. And the one who lights makes three. מכאן ואילך, Mikan
va-eilach, after the first day, מדליק מברך שתים ורואה מברך אחת. madlik
mevareich shtayim ve-roeh mevareich achat. And it becomes two and one. We're
going to say in a minute what it is, you probably already
know. מאי ממעט? Mai mimaeit? Which one do you take away after
day one? ממעט זמן. Mimaeit zman. You take away שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. זמן
Zman refers to שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. Shehecheyanu ve-kiyemanu ve-higiyanu lazman
hazeh. Okay, because
you don't say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu after the first day, right? Once you
said שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, once you came to this new time, you don't
no longer like, you know, you say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu the first night
of יום טוב, Yom Tov, you don't say it every other day
of יום טוב, Yom Tov, every other day of the חג. chag.
So it's already the new time. You said, you say once שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu for the period, not twice. So you don't say זמן zman
afterward. So the גמרא Gemara said, by the way I should say
for some reason you didn't say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on the first night,
you forgot or whatever, you would say it on a later night.
Okay, it's not that, מה, mah, you
lit the first night didn't say שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu?
Yeah, you lit or you didn't light, whatever happened, if you didn't
say the ברכה berachah שהחיינו Shehecheyanu you say it on another night.
Okay, but but if you,
but once you've said שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, it's not like somehow the second
night is not a new time, but it's that it's already included
in the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu that you said on the first night basically.
So if you said on the first night you don't say it
on another. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי נס? u-mai neis?
How about not saying the ברכה berachah of שעשה נסים לאבותינו? she-asah
nisim la-avoteinu? Right, once you've mentioned the נס, neis, isn't this all
presumably a continuation of the same נס? neis? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, נס כל יומא איתא. neis kol yoma ita.
The miracle was every day. Why was the miracle every day? Well,
it works according to the emphasis on the נס פך השמן. neis
pach hashemen. Right, if you say that the whole idea was like
eight days of dedication and it focused on the war, it's harder
to argue why you say שעשה נסים she-asah nisim every single day.
Although even so, it depends on how you frame it. You're not
necessarily saying that today a miracle was done. If the reason you
say שעשה נסים she-asah nisim is because הדלקת נרות hadlakat nerot is
פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, so then you are in order to make
that act of lighting פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, you're saying שעשה נסים.
she-asah nisim. I want to, I want to, you know, publicize the
miracle that was done. I don't have to say that a separate
miracle was done today from yesterday. But for eight days I'm publicizing
the fact of the miracle. But the בבלי Bavli doesn't take that
approach. It approach, it says that look, it's about each, it's about
acknowledging the separate miracle of each day and therefore there was a
separate miracle each day and you can say
שעשה נסים. she-asah nisim. Just one second. of the miracle, of
the מצוה. mitzvah. So מברך, mivarech, right, אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להדליק
נר של חנוכה, Asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu l'hadlik ner shel Chanukah, like
we said earlier.
Again, these סוגיות sugyot were in, they weren't all put together originally
this way. So I can't say, oh didn't we say it before.
Our chronology is not the chronology in which these were said. This
is a composite text. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
earlier was referring to what this later סוגיא sugya concluded. Okay, so
anyway, so we say the ברכה bracha of אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו.
Asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu. Now some have the גירסא girsa that at
this stage it just lists all three together. If you look at
the side, it also says ברוך אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם שעשה
נסים ושהחיינו, Baruch atah Hashem Elokeinu melech ha'olam she'asah nisim v'shehecheyanu, right,
so that lists all three although we implicitly already said the first
two of the three. Now it should be clear what the point
is. On the first night you say all three. On the second
night you say only, only
להדליק נר l'hadlik ner and שעשה נסים. she'asah nisim. You no longer
say שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. If you're not lighting, you're just seeing, for some
reason you're not lighting, then when like, then you say, I don't
know, let's say okay מדליקין עליו בביתו, madlikin alav b'veito, but you're
traveling somewhere and for whatever reason if you try to put a
מנורה menorah in your hotel room they're going to kick you out
and they're going to call the fire department or whatever. So you
can't light. Okay, but they מדליקין עליו בביתו, madlikin alav b'veito, but
you happen to be walking by and you see somebody else's חנוכה
Chanukah light. So then you say שעשה נסים she'asah nisim and you
say שהחיינו shehecheyanu because the שעשה נסים she'asah nisim and שהחיינו shehecheyanu
do not require you to do the act of the מצוה. mitzvah.
The שעשה נסים she'asah nisim is once you are engaged in the
even on the receiving end of the פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa of
the חנוכה Chanukah lights, you can say the שעשה נסים. she'asah nisim.
And once the חנוכה Chanukah lights are sort of
bring you into the significance of the time, you can say the
שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. So the first night you would say two and the
second night you would only say one, you would only say שעשה
נסים. she'asah nisim. Okay. Yes?
But if you're saying, so it sounds like you're saying שהחיינו shehecheyanu
is just on the lights? Because you can say it in the
time, let's say מעריב Maariv I said, I said על הנסים al
hanisim in my מעריב, Maariv,
then I can say, after I'm done שהחיינו shehecheyanu now, it's sort
of like when the day comes, right? I can say שהחיינו.
shehecheyanu. Well, but we don't do that. We link שהחיינו, shehecheyanu, we
link שהחיינו shehecheyanu to specific ritual acts. We don't just abstractly say,
I mean after you buy a new suit or whatever, fine. But
in the שהחיינו shehecheyanu in the context of the מועדים, moadim, we
always anchor in either a מצוה mitzvah of the מועד moed like
סוכה Sukkah or whatever, or a specific ritual act that sanctifies the
day like קידוש. Kiddush.
So here we would be seeing it, you're saying it's still connected
to it by the fact that...
You're connected to the הדלקת נרות, hadlakat nerot, correct, but you do
not just say שהחיינו shehecheyanu in the abstract. Okay. Yes?
So if somebody's traveling the first day and he sees the lamps,
but he knows he's going to be home the next day and
lighting his own, does he wait to say שהחיינו? shehecheyanu?
I don't think so. I mean, I don't think why you should.
The שהחיינו shehecheyanu is the first time that you've sort of engaged
in that מצות היום mitzvat hayom or whatever, right, yes. You'd say
שהחיינו shehecheyanu even if you're
traveling home and you see it, and you'd wait, right? You know
you're going...
I suppose you could. Right, I don't know anybody, it's a good
point. Then you could say that happens every day, right? You're walking
home, you have it, yeah, yeah, right, yeah, yeah, you're right. That's
a good point. Our practice is to do it all with your
מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah if that's happening on the same night. Right,
right. That's certainly true. Okay. Okay. Now
the גמרא Gemara says, a very interesting גמרא Gemara here, והיכן צונו,
V'heichan tzivanu, where did God command us? What do you mean? This
is a rabbinic מצוה. mitzvah. So the גמרא Gemara says, רב אוייא
Rav Avya אמר amar מלא תסור. mi'lo tasur.
It says you shall not sway from what the rabbis tell you
right and left, so God is telling you to listen to the
rabbis. רב נחמיה Rav Nechemiah or some have a different גירסא girsa
רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak אמר amar שאל אביך
ויגדך זקניך
ויאמרו לך. She'al avicha v'yagedcha zkeinecha v'yomru lach. Ask your father, he'll
tell you, your elders and they'll tell you. So you're supposed to
listen to the rabbis. Now I want to again say something briefly.
This text is used in a lot of contexts. First of all,
why all of a sudden does the גמרא Gemara ask like והיכן
צונו? v'heichan tzivanu? I mean how about the fact that you say
אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על נטילת ידים, Asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu al
netilat yadayim, right, והיכן צונו? v'heichan tzivanu? So you could say אי
הכי נמי, ee hachi nami, it could have been asked there. And
the point is though, it really does raise a question when the
rabbis are not just instituting safeguards but they're instituting new rituals, like
מעשה מצוות, ma'aseh mitzvot, and in a way almost it has a
ritual aspect, they institute תפילה. tefillah. Fine, תפילה tefillah is תפילה, tefillah,
is praying, whatever. But if they make something like a מעשה מצוה,
ma'aseh mitzvah, a ritual like נטילת ידים, netilat yadayim, חנוכה, Chanukah, קריאת
מגילה, kriat Megillah, that seems a little bit more like sort of
competing with the תורה Torah like a type of בל תוסיף bal
tosif or whatever. Like it's really sort of creating some type of
equivalent type of thing. And therefore adding the ברכה bracha of אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו Asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu really raises like questions about
how can we make this ברכה bracha and even how is this
appropriate. It maybe I would say is heightened by חנוכה Chanukah and
מגילה Megillah because by חנוכה Chanukah and מגילה, Megillah, especially when it's
connected to a חג, chag, the whole idea of where do you
get the right to institute a new חג chag is also a
very important question. And that's why when the מכבים Maccabees tried to
institute חנוכה, Chanukah, they had to say, well, it's like a סוכות.
Sukkot. So we didn't get to do a סוכות Succos and so
on, and the גמרא Gemara has a whole story with Esther, it
wasn't just a חג, Chag, it was also a new ספר sefer
in תנ"ך, Tanach, כתבוני לדורות. Kesvuni ledoros.
So those types of things about where do you get the ability
to do such a thing like this, you know, really gets heightened
not only when it's the ritual combined with a whole new type
of a חג. Chag. And therefore the גמרא Gemara really asks, like,
okay, you know, it's after in the form of the ברכה, Bracha,
but I think it's a bigger question about how do we sort
of, you know, sort of see that this is appropriate and acceptable
and how do we even make a ברכה Bracha on it? Now
the answer of לא תסור Lo Sasur is given and the answer
of שאל אביך. Sh'al Avicha. There's an interesting debate of ראשונים, Rishonim,
of רמב"ם Rambam and רמב"ן, Ramban, whether you really violate לא תסור
Lo Sasur when you violate a דרבנן. D'rabbanan. The רמב"ם Rambam says
that you do, that even on rabbinic edicts if you violate them,
you can violate the דאורייתא d'Oraisa mandate, you know, מצוה Mitzvah of
לא תסור. Lo Sasur. The רמב"ן Ramban says and every דרבנן D'rabbanan
would be a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. So I don't want to go into
the whole answer about that, but the point is that the רמב"ן,
Ramban, the רמב"ם Rambam and the רמב"ן Ramban really debate, if you
will, the two answers of the גמרא, Gemara, at least if you
treat these answers literally and not just talking about like, you know,
where the, where the authority comes from, but literally, if the first
one is saying you violate לא תסור, Lo Sasur, then the second
one is saying, no, you don't violate לא תסור. Lo Sasur. The
rabbis still have authority and we're told to listen to the rabbis,
שאל אביך ויגדך. Sh'al Avicha V'yagedcha. Part of rabbinic Judaism essentially assumes
that, that we follow the rabbinic traditions and that we listen to
the rabbis, but that doesn't necessarily mean that you have to say
that we violate a biblical מצוה. Mitzvah. But nevertheless, that is a
part of what, you know, our understanding, our whole מסורה Masorah is
listening to their authority, so that is understood as וצונו V'tzivanu as
being backed by God even if it's not necessarily a specific prohibition
and a מצוה. Mitzvah. Okay, so now, so there's a lot there.
But now the גמרא Gemara continues. מתיבי רב עמרם. Masvi Rav Amram.
So רב עמרם Rav Amram asks of this idea that you make
a ברכה Bracha on rabbinic מצות. Mitzvos. דמאי מערבין בו ומשתתפין בו.
Demai m'arvin bo umishtatfin bo. דמאי, Demai, which is grain you're supposed
to take תרומות—well Trumos מעשרות Ma'asros from because you bought it from
the עם הארץ Am ha'Aretz and you're not certain that תרומות ומעשרות
Trumos u'Ma'asros were taken, or מעשרות Ma'asros were taken.
So anyway, you can still use it for an עירוב, Eiruv, like
a, you know, an עירוב חצירות Eiruv Chatzeiros and you can, or
שיתופי מבואות, Shitufei Mevo'os, similarly when these different courtyards or houses get
together to be considered like one domain and you all join in
on some food because the principle about דמאי Demai is although you're
obligated to take, you're only obligated rabbinically, and even more than that,
sometimes they allowed you—like they allowed you to feed your guests דמאי
Demai or עניים aniyim דמאי. Demai. It was more of a personal
obligation and less like the food itself was forbidden food. And therefore
there were these greater leniencies that we would not apply to forbidden
food, even if you did not separate the stuff out. ומברכין עליו,
Umvarchin alav, you make a ברכה Bracha on it, ומזמנין עליו, umzamnin
alav, you make ברכת המזון Birchas ha'Mazon on it or זימון, zimmun,
ומפרישין אותו ערום, umafrishin oso arom, you can even separate the מעשרות
Ma'asros when you're naked, ובין השמשות, u'vein ha'shmashos, and ובין השמשות bein
ha'shmashos between שבת, Shabbos,
between חול chol and שבת, Shabbos, even though you don't take תרומות
ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros on שבת, Shabbos, and ובין השמשות bein ha'shmashos on
שבת Shabbos here it's only a ספק. safek. So now the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, the fact that you're doing it naked means
you're not making a ברכה. Bracha. So and because that's contrast to
תרומות ומעשרות, Trumos u'Ma'asros, you don't separate naked because you can't make
the ברכה. Bracha. So it says, אי אמרת כל מידי דרבנן בעי
ברכה, i amarta kol mi'drabbanan ba'ei Bracha, if any rabbinic thing requires
a ברכה, Bracha, הכא כי קאי ערום היכי מברך? hacha ki kai
arom heichi mevarech? How do you make a ברכה? Bracha? והא בעינן
והיה מחניך קדוש, V'habi inyan v'haya machanecha kadosh, your camp should be
holy, from which we learn that you cannot make a ברכה Bracha
when you are naked. So the גמרא Gemara says, וליכא, v'leika, you
don't have it. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, ודאי דדבריהם בעי ברכה.
vadai d'divreihen ba'ei Bracha. If it's something that is a מצוה Mitzvah
done because it's a, you do it because you're definitely obligated to
do this, okay it's rabbinic, but still it's a straight obligation, then
you make a ברכה. Bracha. ספק דדבריהם לא בעי ברכה. Safek d'divreihen
lo ba'ei Bracha. It doesn't mean it's a ספק דרבנן, safek d'Rabbanan,
it means the rabbis obligate you to do it because of a
concern of a doubt. They're not saying
you definitely—that תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros weren't taken. They're saying maybe it
wasn't taken. So since you even though it's a rabbinic obligation, it's
a rabbinic obligation rooted in a doubtful circumstance, they're not going to
institute a ברכה Bracha in that case. So, what?
We don't usually frame things that way. We usually say the מצוה
Mitzvah is the מצוה. Mitzvah.
I understand, I understand.
So I would say,
so the גמרא Gemara is going to give other answers. What I
would add to that more also is like I said before, the
reason you can use דמאי Demai for all of those cases is
because although they obligated you to separate תרומות ומעשרות, Trumos u'Ma'asros, in
a way they didn't say דמאי Demai was טריף treif because, you
know, and that's why דמאי Demai has more flexibility than other things
that are אסור דרבנן. assur d'Rabbanan. עוף בחלב Of b'chalav
is worse than דמאי. Demai. Okay and I think that's part of
what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Okay, so wait what's the answer?
Because he still said you need to make a ברכה. Bracha.
So now, you don't make a ברכה Bracha on דמאי? Demai?
Did he say? No, ומברכין עליו. umvarchin alav. No! ומברכין עליו! Umvarchin
alav! Oh, when you, when you have המוציא. Hamotzi. When you eat
it, yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, now what?
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא יום טוב שני דספק דדבריהם
הוא ובעי ברכה.
v'ha Yom Tov Sheni
d'safek d'divreihen hu ba'ei Bracha.
How
about יום טוב שני? Yom Tov Sheni?
We're only doing the מצות Mitzvos on יום טוב שני Yom Tov
Sheni like מצה Matzah because it might be יום טוב ראשון. Yom
Tov Rishon. That's a דרבנן drabbanan
but it's rooted in a ספק safeik and we make a ברכה.
bracha. So the גמרא Gemara says: התם כי היכי דלא לזלזולי ביה.
Hasam ki heichi d'lo lezalzuli bei.
That's so we shouldn't treat יום טוב שני Yom Tov Sheni like
as less significant than יום טוב ראשון. Yom Tov Rishon. Hey, you
don't make a ברכה, bracha, it doesn't really count, blah blah blah.
But by, you know, so that's so we want to really give
it like the type of קדושה kedusha of יום טוב ראשון. Yom
Tov Rishon. So we have to make a ברכה bracha there. But
that's not true by דמאי. Demai. The גמרא Gemara says, so that's
one type of approach, it's rooted in a ספק. safeik. The other
approach seems to be bothered with Dov's question. So it says: רבא
אמר רוב עמי הארץ מעשרין הן. Rava amar rov amei ha'aretz me'asrin
hein. רבא Rava says, it's not even really a ספק. safeik. It's
really like, we really don't, you know, you really shouldn't even have
to do it anyway because we can assume that רוב עמי הארץ
מעשרין הן. rov amei ha'aretz me'asrin hein. So it's like not as...
it's a weaker type of an obligation. It seems to be the
same type of answer ספק safeik but going even further. It's not
even such a big ספק safeik anyway. Okay, yeah, we move very
quickly though because we're behind. Go ahead.
It says דבריהן. divreihen. It sounds like the rabbis in the past.
It doesn't say דברי divrei and other rabbis. One has to... So
is the כוונה kavana only the past, that if it was the
rabbis in the past,
we are obligated to listen to them. That's על פי הנביא יאמר
לך. al pi ha'navi yomar lach. So he's not... it doesn't seem
to be including himself.
That's a good point. I mean, I think that's because they're talking
about themselves as an institution and they're talking historically about the previous
rabbis. The past institution. Yeah, I hear where you're going but I
think that that... yeah, I don't think that that's intended. Okay. And
certainly I think the rabbis of the גמרא Gemara believe, you know,
thought that what they said had authority was binding. Whether they actually
in the גמרא Gemara instituted new ברכות... brachos... I mean, certainly the
גאונים Geonim instituted new ברכות. brachos. Did they institute new ברכות brachos
of the type of אשר קדשנו וצונו? asher kidshanu v'tzivanu? That's an
interesting question. When was the last time that that type of ברכה
bracha was instituted? That I would have to check. That I don't
know.
Yeah. הלל בראש חודש? Hallel b'Rosh Chodesh? הלל בראש חודש. Hallel b'Rosh
Chodesh.
That's a good point. There the debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether
you say it seems to be a debate about whether like the
גמרא Gemara would have had you say it or not. I mean,
it is a debate.
And also that's... yeah, it's a good point, but it's taking a
ברכה bracha that existed in a חיוב chiyuv obligation and extending it
into a slightly less חיוב chiyuv obligation. It's an interesting possibility. Something
like כמו ביום העצמאות? k'mo b'Yom Ha'atzmaut?
Right, and some people...
right.
Well, actually though, that's an... that's a perfect example of talking about
the... past, so ironic. Because as I said earlier, the whole... I
told you a day or two ago, the whole idea of making
a ברכה bracha for candle lighting on שבת Shabbos is גאוני. Gaonic.
It's not in the גמרא. Gemara. And that's an אשר קדשנו וצונו.
asher kidshanu v'tzivanu. So there you go. So there we said a
נוסח nusach of וצונו v'tzivanu on something that certainly the ברכה bracha
only is in post-גמרא Gemara times. And even the question of when
did it crystallize for נר שבת. ner Shabbos. And even the question
of when did it crystallize as a מעשה מצוה, ma'aseh mitzvah, like
we said when we began this פרק. perek. In so far, all
it is is to make sure you have light in your house
on שבת, Shabbos, like just saying turn on your lights, make sure
that they're not flickering because you don't want to fiddle with them.
But yeah, when it became a ritual and a מעשה מצוה ma'aseh
mitzvah is debated. But certainly the ברכה bracha only appears in the
גאוני Gaonic times. So there you go, that's a good example of
that. Okay, let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב הונא חצר
שיש לה שני פתחים. Amar Rav Huna chatzer sheyeish lah shenei pesachim.
We're still doing חנוכה. Chanukah. If a courtyard has two openings... now
the simple sense of this גמרא Gemara means that there are two
ways to get into the courtyard, literally. But the funny thing is
we never said a courtyard was obligated in חנוכה. Chanukah. We said
a house was obligated, household. So רש"י Rashi says it means a
house in the courtyard. That's how רש"י Rashi reads it. Has two
openings... צריכה שני נרות. tzrichah shenei neros. You have to put candles
on each opening, I'll read it like רש"י, Rashi, of the house.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Yeah, exactly.
אמר רבא לא אמרן אלא
משתי רוחות.
Amar
Rava lo amran ela mishtei ruchos.
Only if those doors are on different sides of the house. Again,
reading it like רש"י. Rashi. אבל מרוח אחת, aval meiruach achas, if
you have two doors on the same side of the house, לא
צריך, lo tzarich, you don't need to. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why?
אי נימא משום חשדא, ei neima mishum chashada,
if we're afraid that you'll be suspected for not lighting חנוכה Chanukah
and you don't want people to think poorly of you. So חשדא
דמאן, chashada deman, who's going to suspect you? Because they'll just see
let's say one door and and not the other... well actually I
jumped ahead of the גמרא. Gemara. But let's take a look. אי
נימא חשדא, ei neima chashada, meaning the way רש"י Rashi explains it
is at this stage we think that if there are two doors,
people would think two houses... families are living in the house. It's
a split level house, or whatever, you know, it's a... it's a...
you know, it's a two-family house. So they're going to suspect that
the family living with one of the doors is not lighting חנוכה.
Chanukah. That's what they're going to suspect. So אי חשדא דעלמא, ei
chashada d'alma,
people that aren't part of the city, אפילו ברוח אחת נמי מיבעי.
afilu beiruach achas nami mibaei. Even if the two doors are on
the same side of the house, they'll think that there are two
families in the house and one family isn't lighting. אי חשדא דבני
מתא, ei chashada d'vnei masa,
if it's the people of your own town, so they know that
there's only one family in the house. אפילו משתי רוחות נמי לא
ליבעי. afilu mishtei ruchos nami lo libaei. So even on two sides
you shouldn't require, they know that there's one family in the house
and they're not going to think badly of you that there's not
light on one side. So the גמרא Gemara says: לעולם משום חשדא
דבני מתא. l'olam mishum chashada d'vnei masa. We're concerned about being... thought
poorly of by the people of the town. וזמנין דמחלפי בהאי ולא
חלפי בהאי *v'zimnin d'michalfei behai velo chalfei behai*. So what are they
going to think? They'll know there's only one family in the house.
Yeah, but there are times they'll pass by one door and not
the other door. It's not they see both doors. That's the whole
problem of being on two sides. They're only going to see one
door and not the other. ואמרי *v'amrei*, and they'll see the one
that isn't lit, and they'll say: כי היכי דבהאי פתחא לא אדליק
*ki heichi d'behai pitcha lo adlik*, what? He didn't light on his
front door, this guy isn't lighting חנוכה Chanukah *Chanukah* candles. ובהאי *u'vehai*,
and they won't think, oh, maybe he lit in his back door.
So everybody's going to of course think the worst of you, and
therefore you've got to make sure that you're lighting on both sides.
If it's all on the same side, then they'll see as they
pass one, they won't see in one, but they'll see it in
the next one. But on different sides they won't see the back
door. ובהאי פתחא נמי לא אדליק *u'vehai pitcha nami lo adlik*, they'll
think he didn't light on the other door. Okay, so therefore we
have to light on both sides. So now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
says, so this is now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, Rifka, you, I'm
sure, would have said this, but now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* beats
you to it. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ומי חשישינן לחשדא *u'mi
chashishinan l'chashda*? Why do we have to concern ourselves about what other
people are thinking about us? So I should, by the way, say
whatever answer the גמרא *Gemara* is going to give, that it makes
a little bit more sense in the context of נר חנוכה Ner
Chanukah *Ner Chanukah*, which is about פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa. *pirsumei nisa*,
so it's about creating this sense that everybody's involved and everybody is
doing it and it's being publicized and all that, there maybe there's
a heightened desire that you want this feeling that everybody is doing
it. Just wait a second. Okay. דתניא *d'tanya*, we've done a בריתא
*Baraita*: אמר amar, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar*,
ארבעה דברים אמרה תורה Torah להניח פאה בסוף שדהו *arba'a devarim amra
Torah l'haniach pe'ah b'sof sadehu*. The תורה Torah. *Torah* says that you
have to put the פאה *pe'ah*, the corner, at the end of
your harvest and not at the beginning of your field
before why do you have to do it when you finish harvesting
and it's the last thing is you leave your פאה *pe'ah*? Why
don't I leave my פאה *pe'ah* in the middle? I'm harvesting, okay,
this will be for פאה *pe'ah*, and then I keep on and
I go and do the rest. Why do I have to do
it at the very end? For four things. It's not location, it's
the time. For four reasons. After you've done all, harvested all the
rest of the grain. מפני גזל עניים *mipnei gezel aniyim*,
because you'd be stealing from the poor, ומפני ביטול עניים *u'mipnei bitul
aniyim*, you're wasting their time, ומפני חשד hashad. *u'mipnei chashad*, and because
you'd be suspect, ומשום בל תכלה *u'mishum bal tichleh*, and because of
not harvesting your field. You see what that means. מפני גזל עניים
*mipnei gezel aniyim*, שלא יראה בעל הבית ba'al habayit. שעה פנויה *shelo
yireh ba'al habayit sha'ah pnuya*, because if you don't have to leave
it at the end, you can leave it at any time, so
you'll see a moment that there's no עניים *aniyim* around, ויאמר לקרובו
עני *v'yomar l'krovo ani*, you'll get on the phone to your nephew
who's an עני *ani*, and say, quick, come over, there are no
עניים *aniyim* now. והרי זה פאה *v'harei zeh pe'ah*, this is your
פאה *pe'ah*. Okay, so you'll use it as an opportunity to steal
it from the rest of the עניים *aniyim*. However, if it's when
you're ending the harvest, they got a lot of time and they
see when it's about to be, they see you're in the process
of harvesting, they know when that's about to be, so all the
עניים *aniyim* can get nice and ready. Okay. ומפני ביטול עניים *u'mipnei
bitul aniyim*, wasting their time, שלא יהו עניים יושבין ומשמרין עכשיו מניח
בעל הבית פאה *shelo yehu aniyim yoshvin u'mishmarin achshav maniach ba'al habayit
pe'ah*, because if they don't know when, it could be anytime during
the harvest, then you've got them on tenterhooks? on tetherhooks? What is
it? Anyway, you've got them, anyway, you've got them
every day, they don't know, and they have to be spending two
weeks because they don't know when during those two weeks you're going
to leave it. If it's at the end, they know when to
show up. Okay. ומפני החשד *u'mipnei hachashad*, because of suspicion, שלא יהו
עוברים ושבים אומרים תבא מארה לאדם שלא הניח פאה בשדהו *shelo yehu
ovrim v'shavim omrim tavo me'era l'adam shelo hiniach pe'ah b'sadehu*, because you
left it sometime in the middle of the harvest, if you would
have done that, nobody knows about that, and they see when you're
finishing your field, you're cutting everything down, they don't see anything left,
they don't realize that you left something in the middle and it
was already taken, and they'll think you didn't leave, and they'll say:
ah, the person doesn't leave פאה *pe'ah*, that person should be cursed.
So you don't want people to think poorly of you. ומשום בל
תכלה *u'mishum bal tichleh*, and because of the prohibition of do not
harvest the end of your field. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: אטו
כולהו לאו משום בל תכלה נינהו *atu kulhu lav mishum bal tichleh
ninhu*? The גמרא *Gemara* says: I don't get it. All of this
was explaining why we're not supposed to cut down the end, why
we're supposed to leave it at the end. What do you mean
this is a fourth reason? So אמר רבא Amar Rava, *amar Rava*:
No, מפני הרמאין *mipnei hara'ma'in*. For the reason, one concern is they'll
suspect you because you did the right thing. The other is you
actually will use it as an opportunity to do the wrong thing.
You'll just harvest everything and people will say: why didn't you leave
it at the end? No, I left it in the middle, it
was last week, you didn't see. So anyway, so therefore it shouldn't
give you a loophole to actually not do it and claim that
you had done it. So this is the idea of מפני החשד
*mipnei hachashad*. I should say sometimes the גמרא *Gemara* quotes another פסוק
pasuk? *pasuk*: והייתם נקיים מה' ומישראל *v'hiyitem nekiyim me'Hashem u'mi'Yisrael*, that you
don't want to look bad or whatever. But that's more when it
doesn't want to look like you have violated. It seems more specifically
here the גמרא *Gemara* is making a closer analogy. How do you
know you're even concerned that people shouldn't think poorly of you that
you haven't been מקיים *mekayeim* a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*? Okay, and therefore
it's making this comparison to פאה *pe'ah*. Even there is an issue
of perception. Now, the question is, isn't everybody supposed to be דן
לכף זכות *dan l'chaf z'chut* and so on? The answer is yes,
but a) people are people and they won't always, and b) it's
even in your own best interest not to have people think poorly
of you, and I would add c) it's the community's interest that
we not think this of other people because when you think this
of other people, a) besides it leads to discord, it also can
pull down the observance of the community if you think this of
other people. Just for clarification, so basically what we're saying is פשטא
דקרא is only so
much, because meaning if it has one,
that's only two פתחים pethahim on different sides, then we say there's
חשד. hashad. If they're both on one side, then there's no circumstance,
there's no חשד. hashad And similarly, if you're like a guest and
you have your own house with your own thing, you still don't
have to light if they're lighting on you, they're not going to
say there's חשד in that case because we assume that people know
that you're a guest and that they're lighting on you.
No, but we assume also that people are looking at the houses
and looking that there's נר חנוכה ner Chanukah, at the houses, and
not looking at you as an individual, you know, it's what we
think that their perception is. Their perception is, why is there no
חנוכה Chanukah light in this house? It's not they see Michael, they
say, oh, I wonder where Michael lives, you know. Who knows, whatever.
But they're walking by the house and they don't see a חנוכה
Chanukah light.
Right, and they know that I was משתתף mishtatef with the בעל
הבית. Meaning like when you're there...
No, they're not thinking about you as an individual. They're thinking about
their reaction is, they react to a house that doesn't have חנוכה
Chanukah, lights in the house. They don't react to an individual guest
or whatever. You're combining two different stories. This is, yes.
By that, if we're away for חנוכה, Chanukah, if we go away
for חנוכה, Chanukah we should still have someone light for us in
the house.
Well, that's what Michael's, of course, what do you mean you go,
you mean the whole family you go away? Whole family, yeah. Oh,
so that's a more direct application to this גמרא. People don't know
that you're away. Right. Although I assume that nobody's ever said that,
and I think that the house is dark and whatever, although they'd
want to know, like they could light maybe a bit earlier, maybe
a bit later. Right, I mean if you're
home and there's no חנוכה Chanukah candles. Right, I mean, it gets
back to this issue, you know, how far do you take it?
Right, I mean, it has to be some realistic limit. Okay, let's
continue. אמר רב יצחק בר רדיפה אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Yitzchak
bar Radifa amar Rav Huna. Shh, we gotta get a little further.
נר שיש לו שני פיות, Ner she-yesh lo shenei piyot, if you
have a, if you have a lamp that has two, two like,
they've got a, yeah, they've got a beautiful picture in the, in
the ראשונים, Rishonim, in Steinsaltz they have an even better picture. You
see that? It's got like, yeah, it's got literally two separate pegs
there, or it could be on two separate ends. Anyway, there's two
separate places that the wick can come out. Okay, נר שיש לו
שני פיות, Ner she-yesh lo shenei piyot, two mouths, עולה לשני בני
אדם, oleh lishnei venei adam,
two separate people can do it. רש״י Rashi says if you're doing
מהדרין, Mehadrin, you can't do two separate people from two separate homes
because then you need a different candle, a different lamp in each
home, but two separate people in the same home. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, מילא קערה שמן והקיפה פתילות, mila ke'arah shemen vehikifah petilot,
if you filled a plate with oil and you put wicks all
around the plate, כפה עליה כלי, kaphah aleiha keli, if you put
a vessel on it, on top of the, you know, on top,
so you sort of, well, we'll see, כלי עולה לכמה בני אדם,
keli oleh le-kamah venei adam, many people can use it, presumably also
in the same house. לא כפה עליה כלי, lo kaphah aleiha keli,
עשאה כמין מדורה, asa'ah kemin medurah, if you don't put a vessel,
some type of a plate on top of your plate, then all
these separate wicks are going to all come together in the middle
to be a big fire. Okay, and then it's not going to
be multiple flames, it's going to be one flame. And not only
does it not count for many people, ואפילו לאחד נמי אינו עולה,
va-afilu le-ehad nami eino oleh, it doesn't even count for one person
because the מצוה mitzvah of חנוכה Chanukah, is a single flame, it
is not a, it is not like a, you know, what's a
torch. Okay, so again, because then they'll think you need it for
the light and it won't be this idea of the מצוה mitzvah.
of הדלקת נר. hadlakat ner. Now I should say an interesting thing
about this which is that the configuration of מנורות, menorot,
there's an issue about doing them in a not the same vertical
plane. Like if you do it like, you know, like if you
sort of, you know, some things are like this in a semicircle
because of this idea that the flames could combine. Okay, so that
is a concern. It's a less of a concern about not being
in the same horizontal plane, you know, like the מנורה menorah that's
like a V, sort of like that. Okay, although there maybe some
people are concerned that you don't sort of see them together, although
whatever. Anyway, but it's more of a concern of not being in
the same horizontal and not being on the same vertical plane. There's
also another interesting issue that people ask about using electric light, and
some people want to claim that electric light is more of a
torch than of a single light. Anyway, there are various, there are
various issues around that. Some people want to have, some people have
tried to argue against the electric lights because they say you don't
have all the oil there. Remember, you have to start with, you
know, you have to, when you light it, you have to have
the full amount of oil that it could burn the whole time.
So they say, well, you know, the electricity is still coming, it's
not...
so I think we have pretty reliable electricity. But I always said,
okay, so use one that's battery-lit, so then the oil, right, the
whole oil is in the battery, I mean all the energy is
there in the battery. So actually there are interesting, so you know,
in hospitals and other cases, they will sometimes light
with these electric things. I think mostly people don't make a ברכה,
berakhah, but it is an interesting question if, if בשעת הדחק bish'at
hadachak you can make a ברכה berakhah on it. That would be
a related point. Yeah, good point. Probably not if you say, if
you had a ספק safek of whether you're יוצא. yotze. Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this, אמר amar רבא, Rava פשיטא לי,
pshita li, it's obvious to me, נר ביתו ונר חנוכה, ner beito
ve-ner Chanukah, so if you have to choose between light in the
home, presumably for שבת, Shabbat, or but maybe even not for שבת,
Shabbat, maybe it's because if you can't use נר חנוכה, ner Chanukah?
then you need light What's going to be providing light for you
in the home? So you need to choose between light in the
home, but רש"י Rashi says it's שבת, Shabbos, okay, or חנוכה, Chanukah
you don't have enough money for candles for both, נר ביתו עדי.
ner beito adi. Better to have the light that you're going to
use for the home and not for the... also the חנוכה Chanukah
light, oh, is outside, silly me. Okay, the חנוכה Chanukah, light is
outside, so it doesn't help inside anyway, forget whether you have רשות
להשתמש בהן. reshus l'hishtamesh bahem. So are you going to have a
dark house and נר חנוכה? ner Chanukah You're going to have light
in the house. Better to have נר ביתו משום שלום ביתו. ner
beito mishum shalom beito. Because it makes for peace in the home
that you're not tripping on things, you're not walking around in the
darkness. That's more important. בעי רבא. Bai Rava.
Now רש"י Rashi says it's for שבת.
Shabbos. You could have said even without שבת Shabbos you don't want
to be walking around in the dark in the house, but רש"י
Rashi says it's for שבת. Shabbos. Okay, I had a typo, see.
נר ביתו וקידוש היום. ner beito v'kiddush hayom. Now let's say you
have to choose between, now this also emphasize, you know, seems to
be pointing towards שבת, Shabbos, you only have enough money for candles
in the house or for קידוש, kiddush, for wine. נר ביתו עדיף.
Ner beiso adif. Better to have candles. Why? משום שלום ביתו. mishum
shalom beiso. Same purpose, because it should be peaceful in the home
and should not get, you know, discord either with one another or
just in general frustration. So therefore candles in the home are more
important. Now because we seem to be talking about שבת Shabbos and
because we're saying that it's even more important than קידוש, kiddush, it's
starting to point us to this idea of what I said, which
is not yet explicit or won't maybe be explicit in the גמרא,
but this idea that it becomes, that נר שבת ner Shabbos is
a מצוה. mitzvah, Because it would be pretty interesting that the גמרא
would weigh in favor of, you know, let's say, okay, should I
either pay my electric bill or should I save the money so
that I can take לולב ואתרוג? lulav and esrog? And we should
say, no, no, no, pay your electric bill, it's better for שלום
בית. shalom bayis. You could say that, right? You don't want to
be going around in the dark. It's not saying that your electric
bill is a מצוה, mitzvah. but שלום בית shalom bayis is more
important. But nevertheless, because they're being sort of made in comparisons, חנוכה,
Chanukah קידוש, kiddush, and נר ביתו, ner beito, it seems that נר
ביתו, ner beito, the נר ner for שבת, Shabbos, and you read
it as נר שבת, ner Shabbos, is being seen as a מצוה.
mitzvah, And not just as a מצוה, mitzvah but as a מצוה
mitzvah. that even trumps these other because of the aspect of שלום
בית. shalom bayis. But again, it's not clear. It could be said
the whole thing without saying that it's a מצוה. mitzvah Let's keep
on
going. בעי רבא. Bai Rava.
So רבא asked, נר חנוכה וקידוש היום מהו? ner Chanukah v'kiddush hayom
mahu? Let's say it's between something that isn't about שלום בית. shalom
bayis. נר ner, חנוכה Chanukah and קידוש, kiddush, and I can only
have money for what? What do we say? קידוש היום עדיף דתדיר
Kiddush hayom adif d'tadir because it's more regular? או דילמא נר חנוכה
עדיף משום פרסומי ניסא? O dilma ner Chanukah adif mishum pirsumei nisa?
Or maybe חנוכה Chanukah, because of פרסום הנס? pirsum hanesa? פשטה דאיבעיא
אפשטא. Pashar deebaya apashta. After he asked he's decided, נר חנוכה עדיף
משום פרסומי ניסא. ner Chanukah adif mishum pirsumei nisa. פרסום הנס Pirsum
hanesa trumps. Now תוספות Tosafos asks an interesting תוספות, Tosafos, he says
that's why if it's שבת ראש חודש חנוכה, Shabbos Rosh Chodesh Chanukah,
we read the הפטרה haftarah of חנוכה Chanukah, and not the הפטרה
haftarah of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh because of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa
And this becomes an interesting issue about where פרסומי ניסא gets greater,
you know, weight and becomes a certain weight to trump other types
of issues. Yes, Charlie?
Are they talking about the night קידוש kiddush or the day קידוש?
kiddush?
So presumably the night קידוש, kiddush,
so there's
alternative you maybe don't have to make it on wine and whatever,
and you say קידוש kiddush in the שול shul anyway, we're not
saying you're not doing the מצוה דאורייתא. mitzvah d'oraisa. Okay, I just
want to read, I know we're over, but I don't want to
be too far behind, so if you can give me three more
minutes, we can just get through a little bit more. אמר רב
הונא: Amar Rav Huna: הרגיל בנר, Haragil b'ner, if you have a,
if you're good at the מצוה mitzvah of נר, which some say
means שבת, Shabbos, some say means חנוכה, Chanukah רש"י Rashi says it
means both, הוין ליה בנין תלמידי חכמים. havyan lei banin talmidei chachamim.
Then you have sons that are תורה sages, because נר מצוה ותורה
אור, ner mitzvah v'Torah or, light symbolizes תורה. הזהיר במזוזה, Hazahir b'mezuzah,
if you're careful with the מצוה of מזוזה, mezuzah, זוכה לדירה נאה,
zocheh l'dirah na'ah, you'll get yourself a nice house. הזהיר בציצית, Hazahir
b'tzitzis, if you're careful with ציצית, tzitzis, זוכה לטלית נאה, zocheh l'talis
na'ah, you'll merit nice clothing. הזהיר בקידוש היום, Hazahir b'kiddush hayom, if
you're careful with קידוש kiddush of שבת, Shabbos, זוכה וממלי גרבי דיין,
zocheh u'mevalei garvei d'yayin, you'll have, you'll have like barrels of wine.
Life should only work so well. רב הונא הוה רגיל דהוה חליף
ותני אפתחא דרבי
אבין נגרא. Rav Huna hava ragil d'hava chalif v'sanya apitcha d'Rabbi Abin
Nagara. רב הונא Rav Huna was used to learn by the door
of רבי אבין Rabbi Abin the carpenter. חזא דהוה רגיל בשרגי טובא,
Chaza d'hava ragil b'shargi tuba, he saw he was very scrupulous with
candles. Again, for שבת, Shabbos, for חנוכה, Chanukah, אמר, he said, תרי
גברי רברבי נפקי מהכא. trei gavrei rabbei naski mehacha. Two great people,
men will emerge from this house. נפקי מינייהו, Nafki mineihu, and came
from them, רב אידי בר אבין Rav Idi bar Abin ורב חייא
בר אבין. v'Rav Chiya bar Abin. Notice it was he was the
house of רב אבין. Rav Abin. So the two great sages of
רב אידי בר אבין, Rav Idi bar Abin, his two sons, turned
into great sages. רב חסדא הוה רגיל דהוה חליף ותני אפתחא דבי
נשא דרב שיזבי. Rav Chisda hava ragil d'hava chalif v'sanya apitcha d'bei
nasha d'Rav Shizbi. רב חסדא Rav Chisda used to be learning by
the door of דבי נשא, d'bei nasha, the house of the women,
of רב שיזבי. Rav Shizbi. What does this mean? דבי נשא, d'bei
nasha, it's a question exactly what the phrase means, but it's used
for when the father is dead. So the, it's now the woman's
home. It's the mother's home. So he would learn by the father's
home of רב שיזבי, Rav Shizbi, but the dead father, so it
would be the mother's home. In כתובה, Kesuvah, when the father is
dead, you say the bride brought her dowry, you don't say מבי
אבוה, mi'bei avuha, but you say מדבי נשא, mi'd'bei nasha, from the
woman's home, from the mother's home.
חזא דהוה רגיל בשרגיתא, Chaza de'hava ragil be'shargita, so she was very
careful in the candle lighting. Not רב שיזבי, Rav Shizbi, רב שיזבי's
Rav Shizbi mother. So אמר or stepfather, who was it? אמר גברא
רבא נפיק מהכא, amar gavra raba nafik mehacha, a great person's going
to be born from here. נפיק מיניה רב שיזבי. nafik minei Rav
Shizbi. So רב שיזבי Rav Shizbi emerged from her. Okay. So anyway,
דביתהו דרב יוסף הות מאחרה ומדלקא לה, devit-hu de-Rav Yosef havat me-achara
u-madleka lah, that the רב יוסף's Rav Yosef wife used to light
late. אמר לה רב יוסף, amar lah Rav Yosef, now it's not
clear on חנוכה Chanukah or on שבת. Shabbat. רש"י Rashi says it
means שבת, Shabbat, that she would light right too close to sunset.
אמר לה, amar lah, is רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says תניא, tanya, we taught, לא ימיש עמוד הענן יומם ועמוד
האש לילה, lo yamish amud he-anan yomam ve-amud he-esh laila, it did
not waver, the pillar of cloud and the fire, מלמד שעמוד ענן
משלים לעמוד האש ועמוד האש משלים לעמוד הענן, melamed she-amud anan mashlim
le-amud he-esh ve-amud he-esh mashlim le-amud he-anan, they would do a handoff
before the end of their time, which the way it's being read
is, the עמוד ענן amud anan would go away
before the fire would start before the end of the day. So
again, if it's שבת, Shabbat, it's like who needs a פסוק? What
are you doing lighting two seconds before שבת? Shabbat? Right? I mean,
here playing with, you know, literally playing with fire. Okay. So anyway,
it could be this is about חנוכה, Chanukah, that, you know, by
חנוכה you should light, you know, don't, you know, you know, don't
light after it's already dark, light at the beginning of sunset. Anyway,
רש"י Rashi read it about שבת. Shabbat. So don't light it so
close to sunset, light it right, you know, give a little break,
you know, do it a little bit before. So סברה לאקדומי, savra
le-akdomei, so she thought she would do it very early. אמר לה
ההוא סבא, amar lah ha-hu saba, תנינא, tanina, we taught, ובלבד שלא
יקדים ושלא יאחר, u-vilvad she-lo yakdim ve-she-lo ye-acher,
don't do it too early, don't do it too late. So again,
this could be read about שבת, Shabbat, could be read about חנוכה,
but the end is, do it at the right time.